<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encouragement to charity a sermon preached at the Charter-House Chapel Dec. 12, 1678, at an anniversary meeting in commemoration of the founder / by William Durham.</title>
            <author>Durham, William, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3150</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11788975</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11788975</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49150</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49150)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 491:1, 2483:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Encouragement to charity a sermon preached at the Charter-House Chapel Dec. 12, 1678, at an anniversary meeting in commemoration of the founder / by William Durham.</title>
                  <author>Durham, William, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matthew Gilliflower,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Entry for Wing D2830 cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XIII, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Charity --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49150:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49150:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENCOURAGEMENT TO CHARITY. A Sermon Preached at the Charter-Houſe Chapel <hi>Dec.</hi> 12. 1678. at an Anniverſary Meeting in Commemoration of the Founder.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RHAM,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Sometimes Scholar of that Foundation) and Chaplain to His Grace the</hi> Duke of Monmouth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Matthew Gilliflower,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49150:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Dec.</hi> 28.78.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Jane R.P.D.</hi> Henrico <hi>Epiſc. Lond. à Sacris Domeſt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49150:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 13.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But to do good, and to communicate, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not; for with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Epiſtle, whether wrote by S. <hi>Paul</hi> or S. <hi>Luke,</hi> was directed to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> that is, to the <hi>Jews</hi> that were convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Chriſtianity; and principally to thoſe of <hi>Judaea</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> who notwithſtanding their Converſion, by reaſon of their weakneſs and infirmity, were for a ſeaſon indulged the practice and obſervance of the Rights and Ceremonies of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church; for which they retained ſo great an eſteem and venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if they ſtill expected to be juſtified by them; and ſo did not as they ought to do, preſs on to that Spirituality and Perfection revealed in the Goſpel, of which thoſe Legal Ceremonies were at the beſt but Types and Shadows.</p>
            <p>And therefore the principal deſign and drift of the Author of this Epiſtle is to ſhew, That Chriſt is the Subſtance and Foundation of the Ceremonial Law, which of it ſelf, without relation to him, was of no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49150:3"/>value: but having fulfilled it in himſelf, the force and obligation of it was taken away; and that thoſe Sacrifices and external Purgations, which were onely Shadows of things to come, were now to give place to the true meritorious Sacrifice of Chriſt himſelf, which he had offered up as a full Propitiation for the ſins of the whole world. And therefore preſſes all along upon theſe converted <hi>Jews,</hi> that leaving thoſe low and beggarly Elements and Inſtitutions, they would perſevere in the Faith of Chriſt, and in the Practice of the Goſpel, which is the true and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſervice of <hi>men,</hi> much more acceptable to God than the bloud of Bulls or Goats, or the whole Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantry of the Legal Sacrifices.</p>
            <p>And this particularly is the Argument he purſues in this laſt Chapter, of which my Text is a part; for in the tenth Verſe he plainly ſays, <hi>We</hi> (that is, we Chriſtians) <hi>have an Altar, whereof they have no right to eat, that ſerve at the Tabernacle:</hi> that is, that Chriſt the onely Chriſtian Altar, to which we bring all our Chriſtian Sacrifices, will not be beneficial to them that depend upon the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> which he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exemplifies in the 11, 12, and 13 Verſes; and then in the 15 Verſe, the Verſe immediately prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my Text, tells them what ſort of Sacrifice they ſhould offer, not that of the Bodies of Beaſts, but the true Chriſtian Sacrifice of Praiſe and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, which they were not onely once, but continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to offer up, in acknowledgment of the great power and goodneſs of God. <hi>By him therefore let us offer up the Sacrifice of Praiſe continually, that is, the Fruit of our Lips, giving thanks to his Name,</hi> Verſe 15. And then in the words of my Text pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49150:3"/>to recommend another Chriſtian Duty, which God will prefer before any Ceremony or Legal Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which is Beneficence and Liberality. <hi>To do good, and to communicate forget not, for with ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do good,</hi> that is, to others that need your aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; as far as you can, endeavour to be beneficial to them. <hi>And communicate,</hi> that is more particularly, let thoſe that want partake of your plenty, for the relief of their neceſſities. <hi>For with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed,</hi> that is, this is a Duty which God par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly requires of you under the Goſpel; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of which will be more acceptable to him, than any Sacrifices under the Law.</p>
            <p>The ſubject of my enſuing Diſcourſe from theſe words ſhall be to ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That acts of Beneficence and Charity are in a more peculiar way Duties of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shew what further Encouragements there are for the performance of them, from the very nature of theſe Duties themſelves in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Duty of thoſe that are relieved by others Charity, in way of a more particular Application to this preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt particular propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That acts of Beneficence and Charity are in a more peculiar and eminent way Duties of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
            <p>If we conſider the Hiſtory of the Life of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, and the Precepts he delivers to the world in his holy Goſpel, we may find it to be one of the principal Deſigns of his Incarnation, to mollifie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49150:4"/>the rough and churliſh Diſpoſitions of men; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof to reſtore the decayed Principles of Humanity and Goodneſs to their firſt perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And therefore he made choice of that mean and humble form in which he appeared when he was here upon earth, as that wherein he was moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the beſt advantage to recommend thoſe Principles, by which he deſigned to reform the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted manners of the world. And ſo though it was in his power, yet he took not upon him the State and Majeſty of a King, he affected not Power and Empire, the great Idols of this world, but took upon him the form of a Servant, that ſo in that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe converſing familiarly with the meaneſt of the people, he might the better put in practice thoſe Doctrines of Goodneſs and Charity he was to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the world, and by his example alſo teach Mankind this Leſſon, That men are born not for themſelves, but for the benefit of others; and that it is much more deſirable to be good than to be great.</p>
            <p>And though the <hi>Jews</hi> were generally blinded with a falſe notion they had entertained, of a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and triumphant <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> who they fancied was to go out before them to Battel, (like <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi>) and ſubdue and conquer all their Enemies, Yet we find our Saviour himſelf laid down a quite different Character of the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> in the 11th. Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> Verſe 5. where after <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> in Verſe 3. had ſent two of his Diſciples to him to know, <hi>Whether he were the ſame that ſhould come, or whether they ſhould expect another;</hi> that is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49150:4"/>he were the Chriſt or no: he returns him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Anſwer in that 5th. Verſe, <hi>Tell him</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>what ye hear and ſee, that the blind receive their ſight, that the lame walk, that the lepers are cleanſed, that the deaſ hear, that the dead are raiſed, and the poor have the Goſpel preached unto them.</hi> Thereby giving the true marks by which Chriſt the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was to be known, <hi>viz.</hi> not by his Power and outward Greatneſs, but by the offices of Goodneſs and Kindneſs he was to do in the world, particularly to the Poor, to whom he was in an eſpecial manner to preach the glad tidings of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Son of man came not to be miniſtred unto,</hi> (as he ſays himſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.28.) <hi>but to miniſter,</hi> and to condeſcend to the meaneſt offices of Humanity and Kindneſs to the poor and the abject, which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with great compaſſion thoroughout the whole courſe of his Life.</p>
            <p>This was his conſtant practice, as we find in the Hiſtory of the Goſpel, to which his Doctrine was exactly ſuitable. His Sermons and Diſcourſes to the people were all to the ſame purpoſe: he did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain his Diſciples with nice and high-flown Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, (according to the vain way of the Gentile Philoſophers) which ſhould onely amuſe their minds with unprofitable and impracticable Notions, that tended to no real and ſubſtantial good: But his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines were purely for the uſe and real benefit of mankind, for the eſtabliſhment of Peace, and Love, and Kindneſs in the world; and for the reſtraining and curbing thoſe immoderate Paſſions, which made men miſchievous, or at beſt very uneaſie to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. His Law was the perfect Law of Love and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49150:5"/>Charity, according to the utmoſt extent in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Comprehenſion that ever yet it was propoſed to the world.</p>
            <p>He commands us not onely to love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Friends, with whom we peaceably and amicably live in the ſame civil Society, but alſo that we <hi>love our enemies, and thoſe that hate us.</hi> He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us not onely not to revenge an injury (which was the higheſt ſtrain any Philoſophers ever reach'd to in their Principles, few ſo high in their Practice) but inſtead of evil to return good, <hi>to bleſs thoſe that curſe us, and to ſhew kindneſs to thoſe that deſpitefully uſe us.</hi> He commands us to beſtow our Charity, not at large to any perſons we may have a fancy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to, but he particularly determines it to our very Enemies; <hi>If thine enemy hunger give him bread, if he thirſt give him drink.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the Principles of Humanity and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he has recommended to the practice of the world, refined and ſublimated to the higheſt degree of Perfection, that Humane Nature is capable of. And thus we ſee how this Divine Law of Love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is preſſed upon all Chriſtians, both by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and particular commands of our Saviour; ſo that the obſervance of it is not left to our liberty for a Free-will Offering, whereby we may ſuperero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate; but it is <hi>eſſential</hi> to true Chriſtianity, without which we can in no wiſe pretend to be the Diſciples of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>We are not therefore to think (to apply this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe more particularly to Charity, which I mainly deſign) with the ſelfiſh and churliſh Worldlings, that whatſoever we can ſcrape together, (provided it be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49150:5"/>by means allowable by the Law) is preſently all our own; and that when once we have got it into our clutches, we may diſpoſe of it as we pleaſe. No man in this World is a Free-holder, and an abſolute Proprietor, in reſpect of the Worldly Eſtate, which he poſſeſſes, but he has it from God, under ſome certain terms and limitations, who has made ſome Reſerves, and allotted ſome Penſions that are to be paid out to the <hi>Poor</hi> and the <hi>Diſtreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Rich are only Gods Stewards and Almoners, with whom he intruſts the Relief of their <hi>Neceſſitous Brethren.</hi> Now, if they ſpend the Portion of the <hi>Poor</hi> in Riot and Superfluity, or any other way di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it from the uſe it was deſigned, they are falſe to the Truſt Almighty God has repoſed in them; they oppreſs and defraud the <hi>Poor,</hi> and are upon the matter as Criminal as thoſe that pick their Pockets, and rifle their Houſes, for which their Great Lord will one day call them to a ſevere account.</p>
            <p>And indeed, if the Goſpel were ſilent, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principles of Natural Reaſon and Equity would in great meaſure enforce this Duty. For can we ſuppoſe, that God, the Wiſe Creator and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of all things, who regardeth not the <hi>high looks of the Proud, and is no Reſpecter of Perſons,</hi> ſhould be ſo favourable and partial to the Rich, and to the Great, as to beſtow upon them ſuch Plenty and Superfluity, without ſome Reſervation, for the neceſſary Support, at leaſt, of thoſe who have the ſame Common Principles of Nature, and are equally the Workmanſhip of his own Hands.</p>
            <p>Or, if Societies of men were joyned together meerly by compact, can we reaſonably think that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49150:6"/>the meaner and lower ſort of People ſhould ever willingly conſent, or quietly ſubmit to ſo unequal, nay, ſo unjuſt an Eſtabliſhment, as that which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſome to ſo vaſt a height and greatneſs, whilſt they themſelves are deſtitute of the neceſſary ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Life, without remedy? Is it reaſonable that the Head, and ſome other of the more Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parts of the Body, ſhould be filled with preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ointments and Perfumes, decked and adorned in the moſt coſtly and extravagant manner, while no care or regard ſhould be had to the Feet and other viler Parts, which do the common drudgery of the Body, and are the chief ſupport of the whole? No, there ought certainly to be a proportionable care for <hi>all</hi> the Members, becauſe they partake of the ſame Nature, and perform their diſtinct functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the common offices of Life.</p>
            <p>And ſo ought it alſo to be in Societies of men, the Rich, and the Powerful, and the Honourable, who are maintained and ſupported in their Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by the Services of <hi>Meaner Perſons,</hi> are obliged in way of juſt Recompence to take <hi>ſuch</hi> under their care and protection, and out of their Superfluities, as often as occaſion requires, make the low and mean Eſtate, to which the others quietly ſubmit, for the ſake of Order and Peace, to be as ſupportable and comfortable as is poſſible.</p>
            <p>Now, if it be demanded in what way, or after what proportion this <hi>Charitable Relief</hi> is to be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to Perſons in <hi>Want</hi> and <hi>Diſtreſs;</hi> I anſwer, it is to be done without any bounds or limitation, both for the Manner and the Meaſure, but ſuch as Chriſtian Prudence ſhall direct and determine. We
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49150:6"/>ought, out of our <hi>greater Experience and Knowledge,</hi> to counſel and adviſe the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> with our <hi>Power</hi> to defend and protect the <hi>Innocent</hi> from Oppreſſion, and with our Riches and Abundance to relieve the Wants and Neceſſities of the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Indigent,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any determinate ſtint; but according to our Abilities, and according to what the Exigence of others may require. And in this Latitude and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent are theſe Acts of <hi>Beneficence</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> in a more peculiar way, Duties of Goſpel: which was the firſt Particular.</p>
            <p>But, beſides this obligation of Duty, I ſhall, as I propoſed, ſhew,</p>
            <p>Secondly, The farther Encouragements we have to the Performance of theſe Acts of <hi>Beneficence</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> from their own nature: in that,</p>
            <p>Firſt, They are <hi>agreeable</hi> to the Principles of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,</hi> and highly <hi>grateful</hi> to a Generous temper in the very Performance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They give us great ſatisfaction of Mind at the time of our Death.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They make us live in the World after Death, by perpetuating our Names and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They lay a good and ſure foundation for Everlaſting Life in the World that is to come.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Theſe Acts of <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> are agreeable to the Principles of Nature, and highly grateful to a Generous Temper in the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</p>
            <p>However, Atheiſtical Perſons, to make way for their falſe and impious Principles, think fit to ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> repreſenting Men as Wolves
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49150:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Tygres, and Beaſts of Prey, prone to tear and devour one another, and at liberty to do it by their <hi>Natural Principles;</hi> yet this is an impudent and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Slander of their own and the Devils devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, whereby God is diſhonoured and Mankind abuſed.</p>
            <p>The Law of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> is the firſt and moſt Ancient Law, and has a direct foundation in <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelf, being interwoven in the very frame and contexture of our Bodies; We are not hewn out of a Rock that is obdurate and inſenſible, but are made up of the ſofter and more relenting Principles of Fleſh and Blood, which would incline us to be kind, merciful, and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, were it not that <hi>Pride, Ambition, Luſt,</hi> and <hi>Worldly-mindeclneſs</hi> (Creatures of the Devil) did by degrees corrupt and vitiate the true Principles and Inclinations of <hi>Nature,</hi> and choak thoſe ſeeds of Humanity (which though oppreſſed) lye deeply rooted in <hi>every</hi> mans heart.</p>
            <p>But to a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>generous Temper</hi> nothing is ſo grateful and voluptuous as to do <hi>Good,</hi> and diſcharge its Pity in ſome kind and charitable Office. <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelf is powerful within, who with great Zeal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes in the behalf of the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Afflicted,</hi> and to be ſure, pleads heartily upon that Argument, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe then pleads for Self, that ſhe may thereby allay the Pain of her Compaſſion, and eaſe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of her own Bowels.</p>
            <p>And ſurely any ingenious Perſon, that has been exerciſed in the Practice of this delightful Duty of <hi>Charity,</hi> will not eſteem his Obligation to it to be any burden or heavy Impoſition; but will chearfully
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49150:7"/>and joyfully take the advantage of every Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of performing it, for the very Pleaſure and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of mind that attends it.</p>
            <p>Now though this is an Entertainment with which few <hi>Worldlings</hi> and <hi>ill natur'd men</hi> are acquainted, yet to <hi>well affected Minds</hi> it is moſt pleaſant, and the parting with Riches in ſuch a way is much more delightful than either the getting or ſpending of them upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Pleaſure of thus doing <hi>Good</hi> is far greater than that of receiving it. To relieve a Poor afflicted man in his Diſtreſs, and to reſcue him from the Evils with which he was oppreſſed, is a God-like act, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling that of the Creation, a Prerogative Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the Almighty communicated to poor mortal Creatures, whereby they <hi>become</hi> (what our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents vainly affected by their Diſobedience) <hi>even as Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For he that is thus enabled to raiſe a poor forlorn Creature, that is deſtitute of Help, and give him Comfort (a new and an unknown thing to him) does, as it were, create ſuch a man, and bring him out of Nothing, and he that relieves one faln from a proſperous State into Miſery and Diſtreſs, raiſes him in a manner from the Dead, and endues him with a ſecond Life.</p>
            <p>Now what greater Dignity and Honour than this can Humane Nature be capable of? or what ſhould more reaſonably ſatisfie the utmoſt Ambition of men, than to be thus put in the Place of God himſelf, to be clothed with the Robes of his Royalty, and have the Signature of that Power, which is Divine, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed upon them? And thus we ſee how the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49150:8"/>of this Duty of <hi>Charity,</hi> is both Delightful and Honourable, and every way agreeable to the Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of a great and generous Mind: which was the firſt Encouragement propoſed, from the Nature of the Duty it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the Performance of theſe Duties of <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> is highly agreeable and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to our Natures, ſo will the Reflection upon it give us great Conſolation at the hour of Death.</p>
            <p>And certainly there is nothing a man ought more to labour after, than that he may ſo frame his Life, that he may with Quiet and Confidence leave this World when God ſhall call him hence; and if he cannot attain to this, he can never eſteem himſelf happy in any Condition whatſoever, becauſe thoſe ſad apprehenſions he will have at that laſt and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hour, if he be not thus prepared, will deface and utterly blot out the Remembrance of all the Joyes and the Pleaſures of his former Life.</p>
            <p>Now there is nothing does ſo cheer and revive a mans Spirit at his Death, (except the intereſt he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends in the merits of Chriſt) as the Reflection upon the <hi>Good</hi> he has done in the World in his Life time; then will his Alms and Oblations, and all the Offices of Kindneſs he has done, preſent themſelves before him to his unſpeakable comfort, and ſupport his fainting and drooping Spirit, in that time of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> great Diſtreſs. When the Remembrance of all worldly Felicity and Greatneſs will bring nothing along with it, but Torment and Vexation of Spirit. The Epicure will find <hi>then</hi> but little Comfort when he ſhall conſider with himſelf, how he has ſpent the Portion of the <hi>Poor</hi> in Riot and Luxury, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49150:8"/>pampered his Luſts with that which ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed their hungry Bowels.</p>
            <p>The moſt Magnificent and Stately Monarch will not then be at all affected with the Pomp and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his former Life, nor be pleaſed with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe great and bloody Exploits, whereby he has made himſelf terrible to the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Nations. Though he has conquered and ſubdued Kingdomes, and ſet up the Trophies of his Victories in every Place, yet what Comfort will all this give him, when he is at the point to die? Will the Plains ſtrowed with the dead Bodies of his van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed Enemies be a Scene of Delight to his diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and diſordered Fancy? or the Lamentation of Widows and Orphans, which his Sword has made, be muſick in his Eares, and drive away the Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly from his Heart, at that uncomfortable hour? No, the Memory of his former Oppreſſions and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties will <hi>then</hi> torment him, the frightful Ghoſts of thoſe thouſands, which for his Luſt, or his Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or his Avarice, he has murder'd and deſtroy'd, will ſtare him in the Face, and make dreadful Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon his guilty and troubled Mind; and ſo he muſt needs leave the World in great Horrour and Confuſion. But the good Deeds of the juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and refreſh his Spirit, when he lies upon his bed of languiſhing, and ſo he ſurrenders up his Soul with Conſidence into the hands of God the Juſt and Righteous Judge. It pleaſes him then to think, that he has not been hurtful, nor altogether unprofitable to the World, having done ſomething for the good of it before he left it; eſpecially if he have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the ſettlement of his Charity to ſucceeding ages
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49150:9"/>he may then be content and well pleaſed to put off mortality, and live in thoſe Works of Piety he leaves behind; for the Deſign and End of his Life, having been only to do Good, he will eaſily be diſpoſed to die willingly, when he knows he ſhall continue his doing of Good after his Death; he will without any Trouble part with Life, becauſe he is to enjoy the true benefits of it, when he is dead, living more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireably this way, than in a natural Off-ſpring, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by moſt men fondly imagine they perpetuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>For the Affinity of Blood will ſoon be worn out, and what Concern and Intereſt has a man in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Poſterity? beſides, he knows not how ſoon it may degenerate and prove unworthy to inherit his labours; and this very Conſideration caſt a damp upon <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of men, in the midſt of his Greatneſs, 2 <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 18.19. <hi>I hated,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>all the Labour I had taken under the Sun, becauſe I muſt leave it to the man that ſhall be after me, and who knoweth whither he ſhall be a Wiſe man or a Fool? yet ſhall he have Rule over all my Labour wherein I have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houred, and wherein I have ſhew'd my ſelf Wiſe under the Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But a man that does what good he can in his Life time, and then leaves the remainder of his Subſtance for an Inheritance to the <hi>Poor</hi> when he dies, ſatisfies himſelf, that what he leaves behind is diſpoſed of to Pious uſes, according to his hearts deſire, and by this means he makes the moſt of this World, that is poſſible, enjoying it as much and as far as is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with this State of Mortality, and perpetuates his Memory to the beſt Advantage to ſucceeding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49150:9"/>Generations; which leads me to the third Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement propoſed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Acts of <hi>Beneficence</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> do after the beſt and moſt honourable way perpetuate our Names and Memories to Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A good Name</hi> (ſays <hi>Solomon) is as precious Oyntment;</hi> and there is nothing which the more Ingenious part of mankind more earneſtly affect, than a good Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and to leave a fair remembrance of themſelves and their Actions, to the Ages that are to come: but the greater part of men being blinded with Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Vain-glory, court a falſe Reputation, and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> rather to leave a <hi>great</hi> than a <hi>good</hi> Name behind them.</p>
            <p>In vain do great Princes think to perpetuate their Memories, by magnificent and ſtately Buildings of Stone or Marble, for Poſterity to gaze on, which add nothing to <hi>their</hi> true Honour, but are rather Records and Monuments of their Pride and Vanity.</p>
            <p>In vain do the great Troublers of the world en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be magnified in Story for their mighty <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> (a Gentile word in uſe amongſt the <hi>great,</hi> whereby Murder and Robbery are expreſſed in a more civil and courtly manner;) for inſtead of that Glory and Renown they think to get, they bring (in the opinion of all good and vertuous men) a ſcandal and an everlaſting infamy upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>For what are the great things they would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of them to poſterity? that they have brought great Ruines and Deſolations upon Mankind, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulated <hi>great</hi> Kingdoms and Countries, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Crimes and Barbarieties <hi>too great</hi> for Juſtice to take notice of. Theſe are the worthy Atchievements they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49150:10"/>deſire to have related, which are ſo far from doing them any Honour, that they are an eternal reproach to their Memories.</p>
            <p>But the Actions of the juſt and good man, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours in his life-time to be beneficial to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, are as a <hi>ſweet-ſmelling ſavour,</hi> his <hi>beneficence</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> perfume his memory to all Generations; he is remembred by the tokens of Goodneſs he has left behind him.</p>
            <p>All good men will do him honour, as a great Benefactor to the World, rehearſing with praiſe and admiration the noble and generous Acts he did in his life-time; how kind, how good, how courteous, how bountiful he was; how he relieved the <hi>poor,</hi> protected the <hi>innocent,</hi> comforted the <hi>afflicted,</hi> and according to the utmoſt of his power advanced the happineſs and proſperity of <hi>mankind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſuch a Memorial as this is worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to poſterity, (much to be preferred before a long and vain Inſcription in Marble or Braſs, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a pompous ſtory of bloudy Slaughters that have been committed.) This is the good <hi>Name</hi> that is the true and proper Portion and Inheritance of the Juſt, whereby he lives in the minds of the <hi>good</hi> and the <hi>vertuous,</hi> with whom his Memory is precious, and his Name honourable; which was the third En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to this ſort of good works.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, theſe works of <hi>Charity</hi> lay a good and firm foundation for eternal life in the world to come, as the Apoſtle particularly declares in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 17, 18, 19. <hi>Charge them</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that are rich in this world, that they be not high minded, nor truſt in uncertain riches, but in the living God, who giveth us
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49150:10"/>all things richly to enjoy, that they do good, and that they be rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, laying up in ſtore for themſelves a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternal life.</hi> Where <hi>S. Paul</hi> gives counſel and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, how the rich ſhould lay out their wealth to-the beſt advantage and improvement, <hi>viz.</hi> that they ſhould give it to the <hi>poor,</hi> and that thereby they would make the beſt ſort of <hi>purchaſe,</hi> even a <hi>purchaſe</hi> of eternal life, and ſecure a Treaſure in Heaven, <hi>where moths do not corrupt, and where thieves do not break tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough and steal;</hi> an Inheritance that is everlaſting, <hi>that fadeth not away, that is eternal in the Heavens.</hi> So that we ſee the onely way to preſerve our Riches is thus, to part with them; for what we keep we are forced to leave behind, but what we give away we carry along with us.</p>
            <p>When Princes die, they cannot carry away their wealth, neither does any of their Pomp and their Glory follow them; <hi>Naked came they into this world, and naked muſt they return; they brought nothing with them, and 'tis certain they can carry nothing out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the good deeds of the juſt and compaſſionate man follow him into the other world; nay, rather they go before to prepare a place for him; and therefore our Saviour himſelf in <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. gives us this advice, that in our life-time whileſt we have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, <hi>we ſhould make us friends of our unrighteous mammon,</hi> (ſo he calls the riches of this World) <hi>that ſo when we fail they may receive us into everlaſting habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which we ſee, that the <hi>poor</hi> which we relieve if they belong to the <hi>houſhold of ſaith,</hi> are ſo many
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49150:11"/>Harbingers ſent before, to open the Gates of Heaven, and to prepare a Place for us. They will then bear Teſtimonie of our Deeds of <hi>Charity</hi> towards <hi>them</hi> in their Diſtreſs, before God and his Holy Angels; upon which Depoſition of <hi>Theirs</hi> our Saviour, the Juſt and Righteous Judge, will pronounce that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Sentence, in the 15 <hi>Mat. v.</hi> 35. <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, and inherit the Kingdom prepared for you before the Foundation of the World, for I was an hungred, and ye gave me meat; I was thirſty, and ye gave me drink; I was a Stranger, and ye took me in; naked, and ye clothed me; I was ſick, and ye viſited me; I was in Priſon, and ye came unto me. For verily I ſay unto you, in as much as you have done it to theſe, you have done it unto me; enter therefore into the Joy of your Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I diſpatched alſo the ſecond gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Head propoſed, the Encouragements that are for the Performance of this Duty of <hi>Charity</hi> from its Nature and Effects, thorough the whole Courſe and Progreſs of it. The Practice of it is pleaſant to us whilſt we live; the Remembrance of it comfortable when we die; the Hiſtory of it is honourable to our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories after Death; and beſides all this, it layes a firm Foundation for everlaſting Life in the World that is to come.</p>
            <p>It now only remains that I proceed to the third and laſt thing propoſed, briefly to ſhew what are the Duties of thoſe that are or have been relieved by others <hi>Charity,</hi> as a more particular Application to this Aſſembly. I ſhall inſtance in theſe two fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49150:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>1. <hi>There is required Commemoration of the Kindneſs thus received.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>An hearty Endeavour to anſwer the Deſigns and Intentions of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There is required a grateful Commemoration of the <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and the <hi>Charity</hi> thus received.</p>
            <p>And this is a return which Nature it ſelf and the common Principles of Gratitude dictate to all men: He that can receive a Kindneſs, and not be at all ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of it, is a Monſter of Barbarity, unfit to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Mankind, and unworthy to receive any Offices of Humanity. And therefore the leaſt and loweſt Degree of Acknowledgment we can make is to be heartily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffected with it, and upon all Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons endeavour to preſerve and revive the memory of our Benefactors, and that charitable Aſſiſtance we have received from them.</p>
            <p>And certainly in a more ſpecial manner all that any way relate to this noble and ample Foundation, have abundant Reaſon to magnify the Goodneſs of God, for that plentiful Proviſion he has made for them by the pious Charity of our munificent Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whoſe Memory we this Day celebrate, upon which occaſion our hearts ought to be enlarged with a grateful Senſe of thoſe great Mercies God has conveyed to us by his means.</p>
            <p>You that are of the younger ſort are to conſider with your ſelves, how great Obligations you have to a Pious Gratitude upon the account of thoſe great Bleſſings you receive in this Place; here are you nouriſhed and bred up with that care, as if you were in your own <hi>Fathers</hi> Houſes; with that Indulgence to your tender Age, as if you were ſtill under the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49150:12"/>wings of your <hi>Mothers:</hi> Here are many of you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued from the ſad and grievous preſſures of Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the dreadful effects of it; and delivered from the Calamities of a low and a baſe <hi>Fortune,</hi> and the Temptations to which it uſually expoſes men to. All things are here provided for your comfortable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, without any Care or Pains of your own; you are fed as the <hi>Young Ravens</hi> to which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our alludes, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 24. you only open your Mouths, call upon God, and are filled with good Things. You neither ſpin nor toil, but are clothed as the <hi>Lillies of the Field,</hi> and what is far more valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than all this, you have means afforded you of an ingenious and virtuous Education.</p>
            <p>Your tender natures are ſeaſoned with early Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Piety and good Literature, whereby (if you are not wanting to your ſelves) you may be fitted for future Imployment, in your ſeveral wayes, to the Honour of God, the Credit of the <hi>Founder,</hi> the Comfort of your Parents, the good of the Church, and the Service of your King and Country. All which great and ſignal Mercies cry aloud to you for a grateful Acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>And you that are old and Gray-headed, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no leſs Obligations.</p>
            <p>Conſider with your ſelves how happily you may paſs your declining age in this Place, if you duly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe Opportunities you do enjoy. You have here a ſafe and quiet Retreat, from the Cares and and the Troubles of Life, being free from the noiſe and Buzzle of the World, and at perfect leaſure to compoſe your minds and fit your ſelves for your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching end. <hi>Death</hi> many times comes upon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49150:12"/>
               <hi>other men</hi> at unawares, whilſt they are in the hurry of buſineſs, and engaged in a hot and eager purſuit after Worldly projects, which makes him more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful when he appears; but certainly, thoſe in your ſtate of Life can never be ſurprized by Death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have nothing elſe to do, but to expect him; and by ſtaring him continually in the face, his viſage muſt needs become leſs terrible unto you. In the mean while, you have nothing to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb your minds or diſtract your thoughts, but are at liberty wholly to apply your ſelves to the Service of God, to make your peace with him, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently expect and wait till your great change come.</p>
            <p>You are paſſed over the troubleſome and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous Sea of this World, and are arrived at an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of Reſt, where all things are calm and quiet, from whence you may look out and ſee the World round about you in Confuſion and Diſtraction, and every one (as in a great ſtorm) tumbling and toſſing up and down, not knowing where to find any Secure and Reſting Place; whilſt <hi>You</hi> enjoy Peace, and Eaſe, and Retirement; a ſtate of Life which the greateſt Monarehs have envied, and have reſigned their Crowns and Empires, and ſtript them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of all their Worldly glory, that they might only ſecure to themſelves before their death, ſome few ſuch happy and quiet hours as you enjoy: and therefore ought <hi>you</hi> alſo be ſeriouſly and thankfully affected for all thoſe Advantages you receive from the hand of God, let your hearts be filled with Thankſgiving, and your mouths with his Praiſe; Yea, let all both <hi>Young</hi> and <hi>Old</hi> joyn together in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49150:13"/>conſort, ſinging <hi>Hallelujah</hi> and Anthems of Praiſe to the Name of the moſt High, whoſe Goodneſs is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and whoſe Mercies are over all his Works. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, A bare Acknowledgment is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; there is a farther duty required of thoſe that live upon <hi>Charity,</hi> which is, that they anſwer the deſigns and intentions of their Benefactors, by living according to the Rules preſcribed them, and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Improvements anſwerable to the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>they</hi> do receive.</p>
            <p>And therefore (to apply this more particularly) the <hi>younger ſort</hi> here ought with all poſſible dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and induſtry, to endeavour to improve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Learning, and Piety, and Good manners; for which purpoſe ſo Liberal a Maintenance is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Aged</hi> ought to ſequeſter themſelves from the World, at leaſt from the Cares, the Luſts, and the Vanities of it, and attend carefully and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Service of God and all holy Duties, that ſo living ſoberly, godlily, and circumſpectly, they may be in a continual readineſs and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to expect the ſummons of Death, which they are daily to look for.</p>
            <p>And all others of us, who have at any time par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took of the ſame Bounty, ought to eſteem our ſelves as great Debtors to the Publick for what we have this way received; we are not to think we are at our own diſpoſal, but that we are bought with a Price and purchaſed, to be a People zealous and ſtudious of good works. Which if we neglect, we are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ungrateful and unjuſt to our <hi>Founder;</hi> none of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49150:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>his</hi> Children, but Uſurpers upon others rights, and who have robbed the Heirs of his Family of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore all of us labour by all means poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to diſcharge our ſelves of this Obligation, by being ſome way more than ordinary ſerviceable to God and the Publick, that ſo we may give encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to perſons piouſly diſpoſed, by the good effects of other mens Charity, to the like practiſe of it themſelves.</p>
            <p>This is our Duty in general, more particularly we that have been bred up upon the ſame common ſtock of Charity ought, <hi>firſt,</hi> to preſerve love and union amongſt our ſelves; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> we ought to be humble; <hi>thirdly,</hi> we ought to be charitable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We are more particularly obliged to preſerve love and union amongſt our ſelves.</p>
            <p>For our pious and charitable <hi>Founder</hi> having paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by his own Family, and adopted us for his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, we thereby become Brethren, as being the joynt Heirs of our common Father; and therefore we ought to retain the Memory of this Relation: and however we may be diſpoſed of, and diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in the World, we ought to carry the Senſe of it about with us where ever we are, as a Character and Impreſſion that is indeleble, the effects of which we ought to manifeſt upon all occaſions, as opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity offers it ſelf, by all expreſſions of kindneſs and good will one to another.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The remembrance of that charitable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief we have received ought to keep us humble.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49150:14"/>
            <p>Be ye <hi>clothed with humility,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 5. Where he recommends Humility to all Chriſtians, not as a looſe thing, which they may take up, and lay aſide again at pleaſure, but as their <hi>clothing,</hi> which is always to be upon them, as a neceſſary Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering to their Nakedneſs. Now if every Chriſtian ought to be <hi>clad with humility as a garment,</hi> we muſt wear it <hi>as a Livery,</hi> as a ſignal and peculiar Badge, whereby we are to be diſtinguiſhed from all others, and known to belong to the Houſhold of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>Men that have been born to great Honours and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and have had all along a continued and uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted ſtream of Proſperity flowing in upon them, without being beholding to others for it, are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps under a temptation ſometimes, (though it ill become <hi>them</hi>) to deſpiſe others, and overvalue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: but when men of low and mean beginnings, who have been lifted up by degrees to a higher ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the charitable aſſiſtances of others, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get themſelves and their Benefactors, and with the reſt of the vain world be puffed up with high and arrogant conceits of themſelves, they expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſcorn and deriſion of Mankind: For as Pride is not ſeemly in any, ſo in them is it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and ridiculous. They ought to look down into the Pit from whence they were taken, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that their Foundation was in the duſt, the reflection upon which ought to keep them low in their own eyes, and check their lofty Imaginations and teach them the more proper Leſſons of Modeſty and Humility; which was the ſecond particular.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, And laſtly (to bring this diſcourſe back
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49150:14"/>again to the immediate Subject of the Text) Having been relieved by <hi>Charity</hi> our ſelves, we are theerby more particularly obliged to be charitable to others, as God ſhall enable us.</p>
            <p>For as <hi>Charity</hi> is a Duty in all, ſo in us it is a debt, and what we have received in our need from others, we are to refund in ſome meaſure to thoſe that are in the like Condition.</p>
            <p>How can we turn away our Faces from the <hi>Poor,</hi> and ſhut up the Bowels of our Compaſſion againſt them, when we conſider what plentiful Almes we have received our ſelves, without which, perhaps, many might have been in as low and forlorn a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as theſe that implore their Pity. Such a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon our ſelves, and our former Condition, ought to encline us to Commiſerate the Diſtreſſes of others; and this is an argument God urges upon the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in a caſe not unlike this, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.34. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>to be kind to the Stranger that dwells among you, and love and cheriſh him as your own People, for ye were alſo Strangers in the Land of</hi> Aegypt.</p>
            <p>To conclude, therefore conſidering what we have received, we ought to abound in every good Work, eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> which are expected at our Hands as an offering of Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for the Mercies we have by the ſame means en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed. And ſo let <hi>us</hi> take the Advice of my Text and the Words immediately preceding to <hi>our ſelves</hi> Verſe, 15.16. <hi>Let us offer up the Sacrifice of Praiſe to God continually, the fruit of our Lips giving Thanks to his Name; And to do Good and communicate, let us not forget, for with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
